The great philosopher Aristotle said
يقول الفيلسوف العظيم أرسطو
if something doesn't exist, there's no word for it,
إن كان هناك شيء غير موجود، فلا توجد كلمة تدل عليه،
and if there's no word for something,
وإن لم توجد كلمة لشيء ما،
that something doesn't exist.
فهذا الشيء غير موجود.
So when we talk about elections,
إذن فحين نتحدث عن الانتخابات،
we in established democracies, we know what we're talking about.
نحن ذوو الديمقراطيات الراسخة، فنحن ندرك عمّا نتحدث عنه.
We've got the words. We have the vocabulary.
لدينا الكلمات ولدينا المفردات.
We know what a polling station is.
نعرف ما هي مراكز الاقتراع.
We know what a ballot paper is.
نعرف ما هي ورقة التصويت.
But what about countries where democracy doesn't exist,
ولكن ماذا عن البلدان التي لا توجد بها ديمقراطية،
countries where there are no words to describe the concepts
البلدان التي ليست لديها الكلمات للتعبير عن المفاهيم
that underpin a democratic society?
التي تُشكّل جزءً من أساس أي مجتمع ديمقراطي؟
I work in the field of electoral assistance,
أنا أعمل في مجال دعم العمليات الانتخابية،
so that's to say we assist
مما يعني أننا نساعد
emerging democracies to organize
الديمقراطيات الناشئة في تنظيم
what is often their first elections.
عملياتها الانتخابية الأولى على الأغلب.
When people ask me what I do,
عندما يسألني الناس ماذا أعمل،
quite often I get this answer.
كثيرًا ما أتلقى هذه الإجابة.
"Oh, so you're one of these people who goes around the world
"إذًا أنت واحدة من الأشخاص الذين يجوبون العالم
imposing Western democracy on countries that can't handle it."
ليفرضوا الديمقراطية الغربية على البلاد غير القادرة على التعامل بها"
Well, the United Nations does not impose anything on anybody.
حسنًا، إن الأمم المتحدة لا تفرض أي شيء على أي شخص.
It really doesn't,
هي حقًا لا تفعل ذلك،
and also, what we do
وأيضًا ما نقوم بفعله
is firmly anchored in the 1948 Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
مُثبت في الإعلان العالمي لحقوق الإنسان لسنة 1948
Article 21, that says
في المادة رقم 21 التي تقول
that everybody should have the right to choose who governs them.
أن لكل شخص الحق في اختيار من يحكمه.
So that's the basis of the work.
إذًا هذا هو أساس العمل.
I specialize in public outreach.
أنا متخصصة في التوعية الجماهيرية.
What does that mean? Another jargon.
مالذي يعنيه هذا؟ تعبير آخرغير مفهوم.
It actually means designing information campaigns
هذا في الواقع يعني تنظيم حملات توعية
so that candidates and voters
بحيث يصبح المرشَحون والمصوتون
who have never had the opportunity to participate or to vote
الذين لم يسبق لهم المشاركة أو التصويت من قبل
understand where, when, how to register;
على علم بأين ومتى وكيف تتم عملية التسجيل،
where, when, how to vote;
أين ومتى وكيف يتم التصويت،
why, why it is important to take part.
لماذا، لماذا تعد المشاركة شيئا مهما.
So I'll probably devise a specific campaign to reach out to women
من الممكن أن أبتكر حملة معينة خاصة لتوعية النساء
to make sure that they can take part,
لأتاكد من قدرتهن على المشاركة،
that they can be part of the process.
وأن يكنّ جزءً من العملية الانتخابية.
Young people as well.
وأيضًا الشباب.
All sorts of people.
كل فئات المجتمع.
Handicapped people.
ذوي الإعاقات.
We try to reach everybody.
نحاول الوصول للجميع.
And it's not always easy, because very often in this work,
وهذا ليس سهلًا دائمًا، لأنني في أحيان كثيرة،
I've noticed now over the years that I've been doing it
لاحظت خلال السنوات التي عملت بها
that words are lacking,
أن هناك نقصا في الكلمات،
and so what do you do?
إذًا ماذا تفعل؟
Afghanistan.
(أفغانستان).
It's a country with high levels of illiteracy,
بلد ذو نسبة أميّة عالية،
and the thing about that was, it was in 2005,
والمشكل هنا كان، هوأنه تم في عام 2005،
and we organized two elections on the same day.
وقد قمنا بتنظيم عمليتين انتخابيتين في اليوم ذاته.
The reason was because the logistics are so incredibly difficult,
وكان السبب هو التعقيد المبالغ فيه في العملية اللوجستية،
it seemed to be more efficient to do that.
كان يبدوهذا أكثر فاعلية.
It was,
ولقد كان،
but on the other hand, explaining two elections instead of one
لكن من جهة أخرى، محاولة شرح عمليتين انتخابيتين بدلًا من واحدة
was even more complicated.
كان أكثر تعقيدًا.
So we used a lot of images,
لهذا استخدمنا صورا كثيرة،
and when it came to the actual ballot,
وعند بدء التعامل مع ورقة الاقتراع الحقيقية،
we had problems, because so many people wanted to take part,
كانت لدينا مشاكل، لوجود أعداد كبيرة كانت تود المشاركة،
we had 300 candidates for 52 seats
كان لدينا 300 مرشح ل 52 مقعدًا
in the Wolesi Jirga, which is the parliamentary elections.
فى ال(وليسي جيرجا)، الذي يعني الانتخابات البرلمانية.
And for the Provincial Council, we had even more candidates.
ولمجلس الأقاليم، كان لدينا عدد أكبر من المرشحين.
We had 330 for 54 seats.
كان لدينا 330 مرشحا ل 54 مقعدًا.
So talking about ballot design,
وبالحديث عن تصميم ورقة الاقتراع،
this is what the ballot looked like.
هذا ما كانت تبدو عليه.
It's the size of a newspaper.
إنها بحجم الجريدة.
This was the Wolesi Jirga ballot --
كانت هذه ورقة اقتراع وليسي جيرجا--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, and --
نعم، و --
this was the Provincial Council ballot.
كانت هذه ورقة اقتراع مجلس الأقاليم.
Even more.
بل و أكثر.
So you see, we did use a lot of symbols and things like that.
كما ترون، لقد استخدمنا الكثير من الرموز وأشياء من هذا القبيل.
And we had other problems in Southern Sudan.
كانت لدينا صعوبات أخرى في جنوب السودان.
Southern Sudan was a very different story.
كان لجنوب السودان قصة مختلفة تمامًا.
We had so many people who had never, of course, voted,
كان هناك عدد كبير من الناس بالطبع، لم يسبق لهم التصويت من قبل،
but we had extremely, extremely high levels of illiteracy,
لكن أيضا كانت هناك نسبة أميّة كبيرة جدًا،
very, very poor infrastructure.
وبنية تحتية فقيرة جدًا.
For example -- I mean, it's a country the size of Texas, more or less.
كمثال -- أنا أعني أنها دولة بحجم ولاية تكساس تقريبًا.
We had seven kilometers of paved roads,
كانت لدينا سبع كيلومترات من الطرق المرصوفة،
seven kilometers in the whole country,
سبع كيلومترات فقط في البلد بأكمله،
and that includes the tarmac where we landed the planes
متضمنة مدرج الإقلاع حيث تهبط الطائرات
in Juba Airport.
في مطار(جوبا).
So transporting electoral materials, etc.,
فكان توصيل المواد الانتخابية ،إلخ،
is exceedingly difficult.
أمرا في غاية الصعوبة.
People had no idea about what a box looked like.
لم يكن لدى الناس أدنى فكرة عن شكل الصندوق الانتخابي.
It was very complicated,
كان شيئا غاية في التعقيد،
so using verbal communication was obviously the way to go,
فكان من الواضح أن التواصل اللفظي هوالأسلوب الأمثل للتعامل،
but there were 132 languages.
ولكن كانت هناك 132 لغة.
So that was extremely challenging.
كان هذا تحديا كبيرا جدًا.
Then I arrived in Tunisia in 2011.
بعد ذلك ذهبت إلى تونس في عام 2011.
It was the Arab Spring.
كان الربيع العربي.
A huge amount of hope was generated by that enormous movement
حيث تفجرت طاقة عارمة من الأمل على إثر هذه الحركة الكبيرة
that was going on in the region.
التي كانت تجري في المنطقة.
There was Libya, there was Egypt, there was Yemen.
كانت في ليبيا وفي مصر وفي اليمن.
It was an enormous, enormous historical moment.
كانت لحظة تاريخية عظيمة جدًا.
And I was sitting with the election commission,
كنت جالسة مع لجنة الانتخابات،
and we were talking about various aspects of the election,
وكنّا نتحدث عن الانتخابات من عدة جوانب،
and I was hearing them using words that I hadn't actually heard before,
وكنت أسمعهم يستخدمون كلمات لم أكن قد سمعتها من قبل،
and I'd worked with Iraqis, I'd worked with Jordanians, Egyptians,
لقد عملت مع عراقيين وأردنيين ومصريين،
and suddenly they were using these words,
وفجأة أصبحوا يستخدمون تلك الكلمات،
and I just thought, "This is strange."
وكنت أفكر بأن"هذا شيء غريب."
And what really gave rise to it was this word "observer."
و ما كان باعثًا على هذا هو كلمة "مراقب."
We were discussing election observers,
كنّا نتحدث عن مراقبي الانتخابات،
and the election commissioner was talking about "mulahiz" in Arabic.
وكان يتحدث عضو لجنة الانتخابات عن "ملاحظ" بالعربية.
This means "to notice" in a passive sort of sense,
وهذا يعني بأن يلحظ شيئًا ما بشكل سلبي،
as in, "I noticed he was wearing a light blue shirt."
كمثال "أنا لاحظت أنه يرتدي قميصًا لونه أزرق فاتح."
Did I go and check whether the shirt was light blue or not?
هل ذهبت لأتأكد من أن القميص لونه أزرق فاتح أم لا؟
That is the role of an election observer.
هذه هي وظيفة مراقب الانتخابات.
It's very active, it's governed by all kinds of treaties,
دوره فعّال وتحكمه كل أنواع المعاهدات،
and it has got that control function in it.
ولديه خاصية المراقبة.
And then I got wind of the fact that in Egypt,
اكتشفت بعد ذلك حقيقة أنه في مصر،
they were using this term "mutabi’," which means "to follow."
يستخدمون مصطلح "متابع" والذي يعني "أن تتابع"
So we were now having followers of an election.
إذن فقد كان لدينا متابعون للعملية الانتخابية.
So that's not quite right either,
وهذا أيضًا ليس صحيحًا تمامًا،
because there is a term that's already accepted and in use,
لأن هناك مصطلحا مقبولا ومستخدَما،
which was the word "muraqib" which means "a controller."
وهي كلمة"مراقِب" والتي تعني "أن يراقب."
It's got that notion of control.
وقد كانت تحمل معنى المراقبة.
So I thought, three words for one concept. This is not good.
لذا فكرت، ثلاث كلمات لمفهوم واحد. هذا ليس شيئًا جيدًا.
And with our colleagues, we thought perhaps it's our role
ومع زملائنا، اعتقدنا أنه ربما من دورنا
to actually help make sure that the words are understood
أن نتأكد من أن يتم فهم الكلمات بشكل جيد
and actually create a work of reference
وأن نعمل على صنع مرجِع
that could be used across the Arab region.
يمكن استخدامه في المنطقة العربية بأكملها.
And that's what we did.
وهذا بالضبط ما فعلناه.
So together with these colleagues,
فمع هؤلاء الزملاء،
we launched the "Arabic Lexicon of Electoral Terminology,"
أنشأنا "المعجم العربي لمصطلحات الانتخابات،"
and we worked in eight different countries.
وقمنا بالعمل في ثمان دول مختلفة.
It meant actually defining 481 terms
كان يهدف هذا إلى تعريف 481 مصطلحا
which formed the basis of everything you need to know
والذي يشكل أساس أي شيء تريد معرفته
if you're going to organize a democratic election.
إن كنت ستنظم انتخابات ديمقراطية.
And we defined these terms,
وقمنا بتعريف تلك المصطلحات،
and we worked with the Arab colleagues
وعملنا مع زملائنا العرب
and came to an agreement about what would be the appropriate word
وتوصلنا إلى اتفاق حول الكلمات المناسبة
to use in Arabic.
للاستخدام باللغة العربية.
Because the Arabic language is very rich, and that's part of the problem.
لأن اللغة العربية غنية جدًا، وهذا جزء من المشكلة.
But there are 22 countries that speak Arabic,
هناك 22 دولة تتكلم العربية،
and they use modern standard Arabic,
وتستخدم اللغة العربية الفصحى الحديثة،
which is the Arabic that is used across the whole region
وهي اللغة التي تستخدم في المنطقة بأكملها
in newspapers and broadcasts,
في الجرائد والإعلام،
but of course, then from one country to the next in day to day language and use
ولكن بالطبع، اللغة اليومية المستخدمة من دولة لأخرى
it varies -- dialect, colloquialisms, etc.
تختلف -- لهجات ولغات عاميّة، إلخ.
So that was another added layer of complication.
فأضاف هذا المزيد من التعقيد.
So in one sense you had the problem
فمن ناحية لديك مشكلة
that language wasn't fully ripe, if you like,
أن اللغة ليست بالنضج الكافي، إذا جاز التعبير،
neologisms were coming up, new expressions.
وبذلك ظهرت ألفاظ وتعابير جديدة.
And so we defined all these terms,
لذا قمنا بتعريف كل تلك المصطلحات،
and then we had eight correspondents in the region.
ثم أصبح لدينا ثمانية مندوبين في المنطقة.
We submitted the draft to them,
كنّا نبعث إليهم بالمُسوَدّة،
they responded back to us.
وكانوا يجيبوننا.
"Yes, we understand the definition.
"نعم، نحن نفهم التعريف.
We agree with it,
وموافقون عليه،
but this is what we say in our country."
ولكن هذا ما نقوله في دولتنا."
Because we were not going to harmonize or force harmonization.
لأننا لن نقوم بالتواؤم أوالإجبار على التواؤم.
We were trying to facilitate understanding among people.
كنا نحاول أن نيسرالتفاهم بين الناس.
So in yellow, you see the different expressions in use
ترون باللون الأصفر، التعابير المختلفة المُستخدَمة
in the various countries.
في دول عدة.
So this, I'm happy to say, it took three years to produce this
إذا وبهذا، فأنا سعيدة بأن أقول أنه تطلب منا إصداره ثلاث سنوات
because we also finalized the draft and took it actually into the field,
لأننا أيضًا أنهينا المُسوَدّة وقمنا بأخذها معنا فعليّا لساحة العمل،
sat with the election commissions in all these different countries,
و جلسنا مع لجان الانتخابات في دول مختلفة،
debated and defined and refined the draft,
قمنا بمناقشة وتعريف و تنقيح المُسوَدّة،
and finally published it in November 2014 in Cairo.
وأخيرًا قمنا بطباعتها في نوفمبر 2014 في القاهرة.
And it's gone a long way. We published 10,000 copies.
ولقد انتشرت بشكل جيد. فقمنا بطباعة 10,000 نسخة.
To date, there's about 3,000 downloads off the internet in PDF form.
حتى الآن، تم تحميل 3,000 نسخة من الانترنت بصيغة الPDF.
I heard just recently from a colleague that they've taken it up in Somalia.
عرفت مؤخرًا من زميل لي أنهم قاموا بالموافقة عليه في الصومال.
They're going to produce a version of this in Somalia,
وأنهم فى طريقهم إلى إصدار نسخة منه هناك،
because there's nothing in Somalia at all.
لأنه لا يوجد أي شيء مطلقًا في الصومال.
So that's very good to know.
إذًا فهذا خبر جيد.
And this newly formed Arab Organization for Electoral Management Bodies,
وقد قامت المنظمة العربية للإدارات الانتخابية التي أُنشئت حديثًا،
which is trying to professionalize
والتي تحاول أن تُجرِي بشكل محترف
how elections are run in the region,
العملية الانتخابية في المنطقة،
they're using it as well.
قامت أيضًا باستخدامه.
And the Arab League have now built up a pan-Arab observation unit,
وقد أنشأَت جامعة الدول العربية أيضًا وحدة للمراقبة تحت اسم أمانة شؤون الانتخابات،
and they're using it.
وهي تقوم باستخدامه.
So that's all really good.
إذًا فكل هذا جيد.
However, this work of reference is quite high-pitched.
غير أن هذا المرجع يعتبر ذا مستوى لغوي عال.
It's complex, and a lot of the terms are quite technical,
فهو معقد ويحتوي على الكثير من المصطلحات التقنية،
so the average person probably doesn't need to know at least a third of it.
فالإنسان العادي على الأغلب لا يحتاج لمعرفة ثلث هذه المصطلحات.
But the people of the Middle East
لكن الشعوب في الشرق الأوسط
have been deprived of any form of what we know as civic education.
قد حرمت من أي شكل من أشكال ما نسميه نحن التربية المدنية.
It's part of our curriculum at school.
إنها جزء من مناهجنا في المدارس.
It doesn't really exist in that part of the world,
لكنها لا تتواجد أساسا في هذا الجزء من العالم،
and I feel it's really the right of everybody
وأنا أشعر أنه من حق كل شخص
to know how these things work.
أن يعرف كيف تسير هذه الأشياء.
And it's a good thing to think about producing a work of reference
وإنه لشيء جيد أن يتم التفكير في إنتاج عمل ذي أهمية
for the average person,
من أجل الإنسان العادي،
and bearing in mind that now
مع الأخذ في الاعتبار أنه لدينا حاليا
we have a basis to work with,
أساس للعمل،
but also we have technology,
لكن أيضًا لدينا تكنولوجيا،
so we can reach out using telephone apps,
إذا، فبإمكاننا القيام بالتوعية باستخدام تطبيقات الهواتف،
video, animation.
والفيديو والرسوم المتحركة.
There's all sorts of tools that can be used now
توجد حاليّا وسائل متعددة تصلُح للاستخدام
to communicate these ideas to people
لإيصال هذه الأفكار للناس
for the first time in their own language.
للمرة الأولى بلغتهم الأم.
We hear a lot of misery about the Middle East.
نسمع عن مآسي كثيرة حول الشرق الأوسط.
We hear the chaos of war. We hear terrorism.
نسمع عن فوضي الحروب، نسمع عن الإرهاب.
We hear about sectarianism and all this horrible negative news
نسمع عن الطائفية وكل هذه الأخبارالسلبية الشنيعة
that comes to us all the time.
التي تصل إلينا دائمًا.
What we're not hearing is what are the people, the everyday people, thinking?
ما لا نسمع عنه هو، ما الذي يفكر فيه الأشخاص العاديون؟
What are they aspiring to?
ما الذي يطمحون إليه؟
Let's give them the means, let's give them the words.
فلنعطهم الوسائل، ولنعطهم الكلمات،
The silent majority is silent
الأغلبية الصامتة صامتة
because they don't have the words.
لأنه لا تمتلك المفردات.
The silent majority needs to know.
الأغلبية الصامتة بحاجة إلى المعرفة.
It is time to provide people with the knowledge tools
حان الوقت بأن نوفر للناس أدوات للمعرفة
that they can inform themselves with.
حيث تمكنهم من تزويد أنفسهم بالمعلومات.
The silent majority does not need to be silent.
ليس على الأغلبية الصامتة أن تظل صامتة.
Let's help them have a voice.
فلنساعدها على أن تمنلك صوتا.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)